Guide to the Harold Vogel collection, 1950-2014
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives.
Harold Vogel collection
1963-1998
1950-2014
C0249
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections and Archives.
3 linear feet (8 boxes)
Papers, newsclippings, photographs, negatives, slides, and VHS tapes documenting the work of architectural sculptor Harold Vogel.
Vogel, Harold C., 9999-9999
Scope and Content
The collection largely documents Vogel's career as an architectural sculptor through newsclippings and magazine articles, as well as photos, negatives, slides, and VHS tapes from the various projects that he worked on. Some biographical information, such as resumes and biographical sketches, is also included. There are also a few awards and certificates given to Vogel through his professional life. The majority of the material is in English, with a few articles and pamphlets in German and Spanish.
Series 1: News articles, personal, and professional papers covers the 1950s to 2014 and includes newsclippings, magazine articles, and ephemera related to Vogel's many carving and restoration projects, including the Lyndon B. Johnson memorial, the CIA memorial, the Marine Corps memorial, and the Gerald Ford Presidential Library. His involvement in the Northern Virginia Community College Stone Carving and Restoration program is documented through articles and press releases. A few resumes and biographical sketches, as well as awards and certificates, are also included, as is a sketch for a sign that says "Dacha Vogel."
Series 2: Photographic materials includes photographic prints, negatives of various sizes, and slides documenting the working process and finished products of Vogel and his companies. This includes the Gerald Ford Presidential Library, the Confederate Dead memorial, and the Yorktown Victory monument. Of particular interest are photos from the dedication of the Lyndon B. Johnson memorial, which include images of Vogel with Lady Bird Johnson and other dignitaries at the event. There are also some personal photos of Vogel's home and studio and Vogel with his dog. The materials range from the 1950s-1996.
Series 3: Audiovisual materials includes VHS tapes of Vogel and his team's work on various projects, including Arlington Cemetery Urns, the Yorktown Victory monument, and a floating sphere for Disney. There are also a number of tapes on the Barre granite industry, as well as a tape documenting aspects of Vogel's personal life. Many of the tapes are undated, but the dated tapes run from 1988-2002, with material on one of the tapes dating from 1966-1967.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Deborah Weitzman-Ward in May 2014.
Biographical Information
Architectural sculptor Harold Vogel (1930-2011) was born in Detroit, Michigan. He spent the majority of his childhood in Germany, his parents' homeland, and was educated and served an apprenticeship as a stone carver there. Vogel became a certified Mastercraftsman in Dusseldorf, Germany in 1953. He returned to the United States in the mid-1950s, settling in the Washington, D.C., area after serving with the US Army. Vogel worked on a number of projects in the capital and the surrounding area, and he eventually formed Wood and Stone, Inc. and the Carving and Restoration Team, based in Northern Virginia. Vogel's sculpting and restoration projects over the years included work on Washington National Cathedral, the CIA memorial, the US Senate Chamber, the Marine Corps Memorial and the Lyndon B. Johnson Memorial, along with many other projects around the country and the world. He and his wife, artist Hilde Vogel-Michalik, lived in Northern Virginia until Vogel-Michalik's death in 1999. Vogel spent his last years in Front Royal, Virginia, and he died in late 2011.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged alphabetically within the following series:
Series 1: News articles, personal, and professional papers, circa 1950s-2014
Series 2: Photographic materials, circa 1950s-1996
Series 3: Audiovisual materials, 1988-2002
Index Terms
Persons:
Vogel, Harold C., 9999-9999
Subjects:
Architecture--Conservation and reconstruction--United States.; Monuments and memorials--Washington (D.C.)--Photographs.
Contents List
- Series 1: News articles, personal, and professional papers, circa 1950s-2014
  This series contains newsclippings, magazine articles, and ephemera related to Vogel's many carving and restoration projects, as well as some biographical information and awards.
  - Artistic Works, including sketches, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Asia Society articles, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles from Building Stone magazine, 1981-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical sketches and resumes, awards, and correspondence, 1950s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes 2 photos of Vogel at work
  - Biographical pamphlet in Spanish, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CIA memorial wall sketches and articles, 2003, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Completion of DC Municipal Center sculpture articles, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Egon Kaiser and Dieter Von Oettingen speeches on stone decay and restoration, circa 1980s, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gerald Ford Presidential Library project articles, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes 3 photos
  - German language articles and letters related to Anton Felderhoff, reproductions of artwork, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - German newspaper articles, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Immigration and Naturalization mail notice, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson memorial articles, letter, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes 1 photo
  - Murray Spalding movement arts clipping (probably for research), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - News articles and ephemera from various projects, 1970s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - News articles on various projects, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - News articles, pamphlets, and ephemera related to various projects, including LBJ memorial opening invite, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Northern Virginia Community College stone carving and restoration program articles, proposal, press release, 1993, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Senate Chamber restoration articles, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dacha Vogel sign sketch, undated (Box 2)
  - Spanish Language news articles, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Spanish Language news articles, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - St. James Cathedral, Seattle project news articles, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Vietnam inscription on Marine memorial - press release and news articles, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Photographic materials, circa 1950s-1996
  This series includes photographic prints, negatives of various sizes, and slides documenting the working process and finished products of Vogel and his companies. There are also some personal photos of Vogel's home and studio and Vogel with his dog.
  - Carvings of hands photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Central America, projects, Vogel at work photos, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Confederate Dead memorial restoration photos, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Disney granite sphere project photos, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - House, property photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gerald Ford Presidential Library project photos, circa late 1970s-early 1980s (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson memorial dedication and reception photos, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lyndon B. Johnson memorial - photos of work in progress, finished product, mid-1970s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Marble fountain photos, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Marine Corps memorial photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Postcards and pamphlets from Marble, CO, circa 1950s (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Rock formation photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sculptures, Vogel at work photos (part 1 of 2), 1960s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sculptures, Vogel at work photos (part 2 of 2), 1960s-1980s, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - State of Maine Library and Archives photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Tomb of the Unknown Soldier photos, 1993, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Vogel and German Shepherd photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Vogel working on George Washington bust, celebration and installation of bust, Granada, Nicaragua photos, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - White marble garden sculpture photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wooden sculpture process photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Yorktown statue installation photos, circa 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Yorktown Victory monument photos, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - 3 1/2"x4" negatives of sculpture, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 4"X5" negatives of Vogel at work in studio, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 16mm negatives - work in progress, outdoor scenes, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 35 mm negatives and contact sheets - Dumbarton Oaks, Harold as a kid, Germany, etc., 1986, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 35mm negatives of carvings, work in progress, prints of Saks 5th Ave stonework, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - 35mm negatives from various projects, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Marble Institute of America letter and slide, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Negatives - 6cmx6cm, 3 1/2x4, 35mm, and slides of various projects (Kuwait fountain, Lyndon B. Johnson memorial, etc.) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Slides of room, people, outdoors, 1972, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Slides of work in process, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Slides of work in progress used in promotional material, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Slides and contact prints of finished projects, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Contact sheets of Vogel at work in studio, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Series 3: Audiovisual materials, 1988-2002
  This series includes VHS tapes of Vogel and his team's work on various projects, including Arlington Cemetery Urns, the Yorktown Victory monument, and a floating sphere for Disney. There are also a number of tapes on the Barre granite industry, as well as a tape documenting aspects of Vogel's personal life.
  - "Artistry in Granite", undated (Box 5)
  - "The Basics of SBX", 1988 (Box 5)
  - C and R master tape, undated (Box 5)
  - C and R 7 parts - copy, undated (Box 5)
  - C and R second copy, undated (Box 5)
  - Cape Hatteras Lighthouse move, undated (Box 5)
  - Civil War monument, undated (Box 5)
  - Cleaning and injection of Jimmy Hoffa, Cleaning and repair of marble vase, undated (Box 5)
  - Disney floating sphere, undated (Box 5)
  - The Floating Sphere - Nuremburg Fair, ATT, Disney, undated (Box 5)
  - Fortress at Sea, undated (Box 5)
  - H. Vogel and C+R Team - Arlington Cemetery Urns, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel - Arl. Cem. Urns, circa 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel Carving + Restoration Team Arlington Cemetery Urns, circa 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel and the C+R Team Urns for Arlington Cemetery, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel Carving + Restoration Team Arlington Cemetery Urns, 1995 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel Carving + Restoration Team Arlington Cemetery Urns, 1995 (Box 6)
  - H. Vogel Carving + Restoration Team Arlington Cemetery Urns, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Harold Vogel Interview, undated (Box 6)
  - Inside the CIA "Stars on the Wall" - Discovery Channel, May 22, 2002 (Box 6)
  - Laminating, Cleaning, Cleaning W. Marble, Repairs of Doughnut, Injections of Madonna, Cleaning of Civil War M., Rest of Tomb, undated (Box 6)
  - Lettering - Research Building, Philadelphia, Cleansing and Injection of Marble Statue, Carving, Loading of Doughnut, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Lincoln, Nebraska - Harold Vogel, undated (Box 7)
  - "Modern Block Exploitation - Drilling and Splitting for the Natural Stone Industry", undated (Box 7)
  - "New Technology in Barre", undated (Box 7)
  - Vigo, Francis, NPS Ind., undated (Box 7)
  - "Quarry and Manufacturing", undated (Box 7)
  - Stone Carving Voice of America, 1999 (Box 7)
  - "The Stone Whistle", undated (Box 7)
  - "The Story of the Barre Granite Industry", undated (Box 7)
  - Tomb I., undated (Box 7)
  - Tomb, Laminating, Cleaning, Cleaning granite, Restoring doughnut, undated (Box 7)
  - Vogels with Stefan Issermann, Vogels at home, with puppy, Von's memorial, Harold cooking, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - WTC, undated (Box 8)
  - Yorktown Victory Monument, October 4, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Yorktown Victory Monument, October 4, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Yorktown Victory Monument, October 4, 1990 (Box 8)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 8)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 8)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 8)